Speaker 1: Hello everyone, this is Attorney General Keith Ellison with Affording Your Life, your podcast about fairness, justice and consumer information.
Speaker 1: This is not legal advice, but important information you can use to help you afford your life. Well, welcome to Affording Your Life with Attorney General Keith Ellison. Today, I'm so honored to have Nicole Smith-Holt.
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): who is leading our state and our country in the fight for affordable insulin
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): and drugs that people need to sustain their lives. You know, Nicole, thanks for being here
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): today.
Speaker 4: Thanks for having me.
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): Well, Nicole, you have a very critical story. It's not a story
Speaker 5: that's always easy to talk about. Do you mind telling us a little bit about Alex?
Speaker 6: Sure. So
Speaker 7: in 2015, my then 24-year-old son was diagnosed with type 1 diabetes. He lived at home. He worked a good job. He was still under my insurance. And at that point, he was still able to afford his insulin. It was expensive, but it was affordable. Even with insurance, he was running about $300 a month out of pocket every time he went to the pharmacy.
Speaker 7: And that was for insulin and diabetic supplies. Well, in 2017, when he turned 26, he was no longer eligible to stay on my insurance. And what we found through the marketplace for a replacement insurance policy for him was not affordable. It was going to run about $450 a month with a $7,600 deductible.
And
Speaker 7: even with somebody who frequents the pharmacy once a month to buy their diabetic supplies, he still would have been uninsured basically for six months because to meet that deductible, he wouldn't have had any help from the insurance company until he met that $7,600 deductible. So he opted to save his money and just pay for his insulin and diabetic supplies out of pocket at the pharmacy.
Speaker 7: Unfortunately, the first time he went to the pharmacy, he miscalculated how much he was going to need to spend that month. And when he was told it was $1,300 for his monthly supply of insulin and diabetic supplies, he didn't have that much in the bank. He had about $1,000. And so he left that pharmacy that day in June without his life-saving medications.
Speaker 7: and did what approximately one-fourth of all type ones have had to do in their life, he started rationing his medicine. Unbeknownst to me, this was what he was going to do until he could afford that $1,300. I think he was stretching it out until his next payday. Unfortunately, five days after he left that pharmacy, his body was discovered by his girlfriend.
Speaker 7: you know, Alec died of diabetic ketoacidosis as a result of rationing his life-sustaining medications. Well,
just so
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): folks listening can understand everything you shared, if you're over 25 or 30, I'm sure you know what a deductible is, but what that means is that if you get health care insurance,
Speaker 8: your deductible is the amount that is all on you to pay up until you hit
Speaker 8: deductible limit.
Speaker 9: Yeah, absolutely. And then there's still usually co-pays after that and sometimes out-of-pocket
Speaker 7: maximums that you have to reach as well. Yeah. So sometimes, you know, having insurance is not affordable. Right.
Speaker 10: You know,
Speaker 7: the premiums are high. And then on top of that, you have to meet that deductible and that out-of-pocket maximum and those additional co-pays every time you pick up your prescription or see your doctor. Right.
Speaker 9: Those amounts add up. They do. It's almost like they're preying upon us. And when you're 25, 26, 27 years
Speaker 11: old, first time venturing out on your own and having to purchase your own policy,
it's
Speaker 12: difficult. I mean, I've been insuring my family for 30-some years, and it's a complex process.
Speaker 12: Situation when you're even through your employer when you're looking at plans and you go to choose your plan that you pick even through your employer They're complex.
Speaker 13: They're complicated. I mean anybody who's had to figure it out knows that For a 26 year old who's
Speaker 14 (lower-pitched voice): just kind of facing
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): the world It's particularly a daunting thing and ketoacidosis. Just so people know when you are a diabetic
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): you know you take the insulin because if you don't take it your blood
Speaker 15: essentially will kind of acidify yeah turns
Speaker 7: to acid and it starts you know destroying your internal organs right and a lot of times you know people ask me all the time well why didn't he call 9-1-1 or why didn't he go
to the
Speaker 7: emergency room or why didn't he call
you
one
Speaker 7: of the first organs in your body that's affected by the ketoacidosis, the acid within your blood system is your brain. It makes you confused and disoriented and you're unable to make decisions. So that doesn't surprise me that he did not reach out for help.
-
Speaker 18: Well,
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): just to keep this totally real, when I sat down with you at this table in my office today,
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): You shared with me something that was pretty, pretty
Speaker 19: sobering.
Speaker 20: Yeah. There's been another death in Minnesota. Right. Another young man, 21 years old, working two jobs. His body was found on the 28th of June from the same thing that Alec passed away from.
Speaker 21: You know,
it's a crisis in
Speaker 6: America right
Speaker 7: now. It is a crisis. It is a crisis.
Speaker 7: It's the amount of money that they're expecting people to pay per month to stay alive is criminal.
I
Speaker 22: don't know that many people that can easily afford the price tag that they're
Speaker 23: asking. - And you know,
Speaker 23: The price tag is outrageous, but if we can talk about
Speaker 24: how insulin was discovered, you know the story.
Speaker 9: Yeah, and actually I was just in London, Ontario two weeks ago, the
Speaker 7: birthplace of insulin. I toured the Banting House with a group of Minnesotans and people
Speaker 9: from Wisconsin and Illinois and Michigan and Indiana. we went on a caravan to buy affordable
Speaker 9: insulin
Speaker 7: in Canada and on that trip we spent some time at the Banting house the home of insulin
you know it was
Speaker 26: discovered by
Speaker 9: a couple couple of great men yeah and then
Speaker 9: given away to the University of Toronto. - Right. - They did not want their name on the patent because they felt as if it was a gift to the world.
Speaker 27: - That's actually, that's absolutely right. -
Speaker 9: Yeah, and so it was given, they actually did receive a dollar each for their discovery. - A Canadian dollar. - A Canadian dollar. - Right. - A hundred years ago, so we can imagine how much that dollar was worth. You know,
and
Speaker 9: They actually won a Nobel Peace Prize for their discovery. As
Speaker 29: they should.
Speaker 11: Prior to that, it was a certain death sentence. They had wards in hospitals that were specific for people who had type 1. Typically at that time it was children. And so they would have wards set up for little kids who would lay in bed all day and just wait to die.
Sure.
They
Speaker 11: were starved. That prolonged the dyeing process, but it was a horrific and painful way to go.
Speaker 31: Yeah. And somehow Eli Lilly got involved. Is that right?
Speaker 11: Yeah. So the University of Toronto said that they didn't have the capability to mass produce the product.
Speaker 9: So Eli Lilly swooped in and says, oh, hey, we can do that for you. And...
Speaker 7: From there on, they have been hand over fist, making a lot of money off of this.
Speaker 32 (lower-pitched voice): They essentially monetized something that was
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): produced and invented for the public good and have profiteered off of it. But it's gotten particularly bad in the last 20 years. Is
that
Speaker 9: right? Yeah. So in 1996, when Eli Lilly introduced Humalog, which is an analog,
Speaker 7: a fast-acting insulin, It made the lives of every type 1 diabetic who was using Humalog
It's
Speaker 7: much more easily managed.
Speaker 9: And over the past, well since 1996, the price of it has increased 1,200 percent.
Speaker 33: 1,200 percent.
Speaker 7: There's been no change to their formula. They cannot use R&D as a justification for this price because we haven't seen any new
Speaker 36: developments. You know...
Speaker 35: basically they're saying we
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): have it you need it pay me
Speaker 37: right right yeah
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): that's essentially what they're
Speaker 37: saying and isn't that what like the mob does right and drug cartels and exactly yeah
Speaker 38: and and when you think about the way it
was
Speaker 38: discovered because actually it wasn't invented because
Speaker 39: it comes from
Speaker 9: right you
know
Speaker 39: at
Speaker 9: that time it was an animal product right so it did go from an animal product to a human hormone that was extracted from humans to now chemically
Speaker 40: engineered analog so there has been three different versions of it but
Speaker 32 (lower-pitched voice): it's still the same concept and the original version of it was invented
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): in the public interest
Speaker 2 (lower-pitched voice): And I can't think of why somebody would try to profiteer so outrageously from it, but they have done so. Let me just ask you this, what you've been doing a lot on this front. What's that T-shirt you're wearing right there?
Speaker 9: affordable insulin now t-shirt that's
Speaker 41: right and you guys got a you got a hashtag we have
a
Speaker 9: hashtag hashtag Minnesota insulin for all or hashtag insulin for all mm-hmm
Speaker 42: how could people join you
Speaker 9: you know they can check out our Facebook page Minnesota insulin for all or go to the overall advocacy
Speaker 40: page which is t1 international
Speaker 14 (lower-pitched voice): right and you've recently you just kind of mentioned that you were in Canada
is
Speaker 14 (lower-pitched voice): canada uh charging folks i mean like the united states for insulin
Speaker 9: no actually you know we kind of felt like we were robbing them blind when
Speaker 7: we left we've done two recent caravans to canada one the first one was in may and we went up through minnesota and we went to
Speaker 9: saint francis
Speaker 43: like they're up to manitoba
Speaker 9: yeah and i think it's ontario okay and then the second one was just in london ontario
Speaker 7: where we went through you know all the five states to get there it was a 16 No.
Speaker 7: bus ride but it was absolutely
Speaker 9: right yeah oh yeah
I bought a
Speaker 9: vial of insulin there the same product that Alec used yeah here it's about three hundred forty dollars
and in
Speaker 9: Canada that same vial of insulin that is manufactured by Eli
Lilly
Speaker 9: in the same warehouse that all of
Speaker 7: the other insulin gets manufactured, just slightly packaged a little bit different to it was under
$30.
Speaker 45: So 10% of what it is here.
Speaker 7: So the group of us that everybody that went spent roughly $2,000 in US dollars to buy a massive amount of insulin.
Speaker 7: We saved
Speaker 46: $20,000.
Speaker 47: Incredible.
There's
Speaker 1: just no way to justify what these companies... But it's not just Eli Lilly. It's also Novo Nordisk. And
Speaker 48: Sanofi. But
Speaker 1: the thing about some of the... Novo Nordisk is actually a
Speaker 49: European company. So
Speaker 50: Eli Lilly is the only U.S.-based insulin manufacturing company. There's only three that...
Speaker 50: that sell 96% of the world's insulin, and Eli Lilly is the only U.S.-based one.
Speaker 51: But even the foreign ones that come here sell it at the premium price, right?
Speaker 7: They do. You know, the three companies over the past 20 years have raised their prices in lockstep at the same time, at the same rate, and they are charging the equivalent
Speaker 52: for all three products.
Speaker 53: Well, you
Speaker 14 (lower-pitched voice): know, as the Minnesota
Attorney General,
I
Speaker 14 (lower-pitched voice): have a responsibility
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): to make sure that anti-competitive practices like illegal price fixing don't occur. And we're suing a whole bunch of generic drug manufacturers for just that right now. It's not legal for companies to
Speaker 56: collaborate, collude, and not compete on price.
Speaker 12: Yep, so we're looking forward to you taking the charge on this and doing what you have the authority to do.
Speaker 53: Yeah, well, we actually have one insulin lawsuit we've already filed. We're
Speaker 14 (lower-pitched voice): going after them on that, and we're looking for more than one way to try to knock these prices down. One of the ways is we have a drug pricing task force, and you're the co-chair of it.
Speaker 57: Yes, I am.
Speaker 14 (lower-pitched voice): Thank you for doing that.
Speaker 57: Yeah, absolutely.
Speaker 14 (lower-pitched voice): So, I'm super happy
Speaker 58: you agreed to do that. Tell me what motivated you to take on that challenge.
- Well, what
Speaker 11: pharmaceutical companies are doing in the United States is just wrong. It's criminal,
Speaker 7: it's costing people lives. On average, we lose about 50,000 US citizens per year.
Speaker 7: Because they can't afford their medications or their health care. It's
Speaker 32 (lower-pitched voice): shocking that they don't seem to be bothered by that.
Speaker 7: No, no, because they know that, you know, behind every body lost, there's two more that are
Speaker 9: going to be needing their services.
Speaker 59: Yeah,
yeah,
Speaker 60: it's shocking.
Speaker 60: You've already chaired
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): several meetings. Your co-chair is Senator Jensen. Yeah. And you and Senator
Speaker 14 (lower-pitched voice): Jensen have had some spirited exchanges at our
Speaker 1: meetings.
Speaker 57: Yeah. Yeah, we have. Yeah, yeah.
Speaker 1: We're
going to
Speaker 1: have them on this show. But one of the things that I would hope you would share with our listeners is,
Speaker 61 (lower-pitched voice): you know, sort of what is your perspective on the emergency insulin bill that was before the state legislature?
Speaker 62: you know I think that our so
Speaker 63: basically what are the bill what would
Speaker 50: have done yeah so the Alex Smith emergency insulin bill would have been a safety net for for people who live in Minnesota who are insulin
Speaker 9: dependent right you know with that rising cost of insulin
Speaker 7: not everybody is able to afford it like my son and like Jesse and like countless number
Speaker 7: Other people in Minnesota, this would have been a safety net to provide free or very, very low cost insulin to somebody who's found themselves in an emergency situation like Alec without insurance because of aging off of my plan or somebody who lost a job or somebody who's going through a divorce.
Speaker 7: you know no longer has coverage sure you know there's countless numbers of reasons you know somebody who has a high deductible plan and their furnace went out or their car broke down and now they can't get that fixed because they have to afford their insulin so it would have been a safety net to provide them with at least a three month supply of insulin to tide them over while they search for a long-term
Speaker 65: solution right
right
We
Speaker 7: never intended for it to be something that was a long-term solution. It's not going to lower the price of insulin. You know, there's other bills that we'll be working on for that aspect. But it was a safety net to prevent an unfortunate death.
Speaker 60: Mm-hmm. And it didn't pass.
It
Speaker 7: did not pass. Do you know why? In the final minutes of the special session, it just disappeared. My personal opinion on that is,
you
Speaker 7: know, Novo Nordisk was brought in as a lobbyist. I think that they swayed the votes at
the last
Speaker 7: minute, unfortunately, you know, money talks
Speaker 66: these days.
Speaker 67: - Doesn't it? I mean, the thing that about that that kind of
Speaker 14 (lower-pitched voice): concerns me is that like, Novo Nordisk and all the rest of them, they're not making, I mean, most companies would be pretty happy with a five to 7% rate of return,
they
Speaker 14 (lower-pitched voice): look at that as chump change and they're like look why should we do that when we could mark up three four hundred
Speaker 68: percent right
Speaker 14 (lower-pitched voice): you know and they don't seem to be bothered by the fact that people are losing their lives I mean you wonder I mean it's impossible I don't want to blame anybody for Jesse's passing other than the pharmaceutical companies
but you
Speaker 14 (lower-pitched voice): know if we would have been able to pass an emergency measure to get people some emergency insulin you never know you don't know what would happen right you
Speaker 70: don't know who's suffering right here
Speaker 69: right now right
Speaker 71: And we knew and we told these legislators that this bill will save lives. And we have shown that recently, that with the inflammation of the Alex Smith Emergency Insulin Act would have saved lives. It very well possibly could have saved Jesse's
Speaker 72: life.
Speaker 60: Well, look, I think
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): that no doubt about it, you have made an important contribution to the fight for affordable insulin.
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): and you are talking to policymakers. They know you. They're listening to you. You are standing there dealing with
them. And I
Speaker 3 (lower-pitched voice): just want to say thank you for that. It's really
Speaker 14 (lower-pitched voice): tremendous. You, your husband, your other friends, and folks who've been part of the effort. What do you want people to know? You
Speaker 66: know, that we are fighting, that we're not backing down. You know, I think that a lot of
Speaker 71: people would have been discouraged by the outcome of the last legislative session and
Speaker 71: maybe taken a break and regrouped. We took our break and we regrouped and we doubled in size and we doubled in power. - That's right. - And we are coming back twice as strong and we won't stop until this bill is in place. And we're gonna push forward with additional bills.
-
Speaker 73: Well, we're gonna be there with you. Thank you, Nicole.
Speaker 74: Thank you.
-
Speaker 14 (lower-pitched voice): Thanks for doing all the things that you're doing and thanks for co-chairing our committee. Thanks for coming to every listening
Speaker 61 (lower-pitched voice): session.
Speaker 61 (lower-pitched voice): And just so honored to have you on the first episode of
Speaker 1: Affording Your Life with Attorney General Keith Ellison. Well,
Speaker 75: thank you.
Speaker 1: Well, hey, everybody. This is Attorney General Keith Ellison with Affording Your Life, the show about fairness, justice, and consumer information.
Speaker 14 (lower-pitched voice): We're not distributing legal advice here. If you have a legal problem, either call us or contact an attorney.
Speaker 14 (lower-pitched voice): But check in and see us next time on Affording Your Life with Attorney General Keith Ellison. Thank you very much.